A Guide to the Manuscripts Vertical File, 1749 - ongoing
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
- Letter size documents,1767-1974.
  - Organizations - Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities, booklet on Jamestown. 1 booklet. (Box 240-5)
  - Organizations - Beta Sigma Phi, Alexandria Chapter, fashion show pamphlets, 1946-1947. 2 pamphlets. (Box 240-6)
  - Organizations - Historic Alexandria Foundation, directory, 1986. 1 pamphlet. donated by W.F. Smith, 2000. (Box 240-6)
  - Organizations - Independent Order of Odd Fellows, Proceedings of the Grand Lodge, Alexandria, VA. April 1876. 1 book. Donated in 2003. (Box 240-6)
  - Organizations - Kiwanis Club, text of speech re: club history, 1932-1939. 6 pages. (Box 240-6)
  - Organizations - Ku Klux Klan, Potomac Klan No. 115, application for citizenship, 1920s. 1 piece. Donated in 1997. (Box 240-6)
  - Organizations - Knights of Labor, A Statement of Facts, 1886. 1 piece. (Box 240-6)
  - Organizations - Knights of Pythias, bylaws and rules of order, 1869. 1 booklet (partial). Gift of Marvin Lee Steadman. (Box 240-6)
  - Organizations - Local Memorial Committee of Alexandria, Masonic Temple souvenir book, 1923. 1 book. (Box 240-6)
  - Organizations - Mount Vernon Band, general laws and bylaws, 1853. 1 booklet. (Box 240-6)
  - Organizations - Needlework Guild, account book and minutes, 1898-1938. 1 book. (Box 240-6)
  - Organizations - Old Dominion Boat Club, two ribbons. 2 artifacts. (Box 240-6)
  - Organizations - Order of Red Men, feast program, ca. 1910. 1 piece. (Box 240-6)
  - Organizations - Robert E. Lee Camp, Confederate Veterans, rosters. 3 booklets. (Box 240-6)
  - Organizations - Society for the Restoration of Historic Alexandria. 3 pieces. (Box 240-6)
  - Organizations - United Daughters of the Confederacy. 3 pieces. (Box 240-6)
  - Organizations - Virginia State Association of Letter Carriers, 45th annual convention brochure, 1970. 1 brochure. (Box 240-6)
  - Organizations - Washington Lodge, No. 22. 8 pieces. (Box 240-6)
  - Organizations - Washington Society, 1812-1932. 3 pieces. (Box 240-6)
  - Organizations - Washington Society of Alexandria, Resolution, February 9, 1813. 1 piece. Donated in 1999. (Box 240-6)
  - Personal Papers - Hooff, John Carlyle Herbert. 2 pieces. (Box 240-6)
  - Plays - The Purple Heart, by W.A. Brown, n.d. 9 pages. (Box 240-6)
  - Postage Stamps - America's Libraries, 1982. 1 piece. (Box 240-6)
  - Postage Stamps - George Washington Masonic Memorial, 1932. 1 piece. (Box 240-6)
  - Postage Stamps - Washington and Lee University, 1949. 1 piece. (Box 240-6)
  - Postal Cards - View of Alexandria from Masonic Memorial Looking East, 1960. 1 piece. (Box 240-6)
  - Potomac River - Potomac Flats Improvements, n.d. 1 book. (Box 240-6)
  - Potomac, Town of - Sewerage system letter, 1923. 1 piece. Donated in 1997. (Box 240-6)
  - Presidents - U.S. presidents inauguration programs, 1905-1961. 7 pieces. (Box 240-6)
  - Programs - Mr. Burnham, First Ballad Concert at Odd Fellows Hall, 1848. 1 piece. (Box 240-6)
  - Railroads - Alexandria and Falmouth Railway Company, petition to Congress, 1837. 1 piece. (Box 240-6)
  - Railroads - Alexandria & Fredericksburg Railway Company, check, 1885. 1 piece. (Box 240-6)
  - Railroads - Government request for transportation of Robert K. Ranck, 1950-1951. 2 pieces. (Box 240-6)
  - Railroads - Orange & Alexandria Railroad, report by U.S. Senate on petition, 1852. 1 piece. (Box 240-6)
  - Railroads - Piedmont Airline Railroad, schedule, 1893. 1 piece. (Box 240-6)
  - Railroads - Richmond, Fredericksburg & Potomac Railroad Co./Washington Southern Railway Co., check, 1911. 1 piece. (Box 240-6)
  - Railroads - Southern Railway Company, invoice, 1900. 1 piece. (Box 240-6)
  - Railroads - Virginia Midland Railway, local freight tariff terms and conditions, No. 5, 1882. 1 pamphlet. (Box 240-6)
  - Railroads - Washington, Alexandria & Mount Vernon Railway Co., pamphlet, 1902. 1 pamphlet. (Box 240-6)
  - Railroads - Washington-Virginia Railway Co., ticket book, 1918. 1 piece. (Box 240-6)
  - Reminiscences - Miller, Eliza H., 1844-1927. 1 book. (Box 240-6)
  - Roads - Alexandria to Dumfries Post Road, 1808. 1 piece. (Box 240-6)
  - Retrocession - Retrocession of Alexandria to Virginia, Report 325, 29th Congress, 1st Session, February 25, 1846. 1 piece. (Box 240-6)
  - Schools - Alexandria Academy, geography book, 1871. 1 book. (Box 240-7)
  - Schools - Alexandria Boarding School. 1 piece and 3 booklets. (Box 240-7)
  - Schools - Alexandria Female Seminary, circular and student roster, 1854-1855. 1 piece. (Box 240-7)
  - Schools - Alexandria Female Seminary, proficiency certificate, 1869. 1 piece. (Box 240-7)
  - Schools - Alexandria Hospital School of Nursing, letter re: cap, 1962. 1 piece. (Box 240-7)
  - Schools - Alexandria School Board, miscellaneous clippings, 1880s. 18 pieces. (Box 240-7)
  - Schools - Belle Haven Institute, catalogue, 1870. 1 pamphlet. (Box 240-7)
  - Schools - George Mason High School, report card, 1932. 1 piece. (Box 240-7)
  - Schools - George Washington High School, graduation exercises, 1939. 1 piece. (Box 240-7)
  - Schools - William D. Hudson, report cards, 1864. 2 pieces. (Box 240-7)
  - Schools - Mahlon H. Janney, Alexandria High School, student exercise book, 1859-1863. 1 book. Donated in 1997. (Box 240-7)
  - Schools - T.C. Williams High School, Labyrinth literary/art magazine, 1995. 1 book. (Box 240-7)
  - Schools - Miss Powell's Select School for Young Ladies, report cards and advertisement (photocopy), n.d. 3 pieces. (Box 240-7)
  - Schools - Miss Tebbs' School, certificate of proficiency, 1882. 1 piece (photocopy). (Box 240-7)
  - Schools - Protestant Episcopal Theological Seminary in Virginia, "Recollections of the Old Chapel," 1881. 1 booklet. (Box 240-7)
  - Schools - Protestant Episcopal Theological Seminary, Catalogue of officers, students, and alumni, 1852-1853. 1 booklet. (Box 240-7)
  - Schools - Superintendent of Public Schools, annual reports, 1871-1887. 6 booklets. (Box 240-7)
  - Schools - Washington School, teacher contract, 1871. 2 pieces. (Box 240-7)
  - Scrapbooks - Miscellaneous clippings, 1895-1898. 1 book. (Box 240-7)
  - Scrapbooks - Virginia History (juvenile author). 1 book. (Box 240-7)
  - Sermons - Leftwich, J.T., funeral of Catherine McNair, 1869. 1 pamphlet. Donated by Ms. Katherine Harrison, 1998. (Box 240-7)
  - Sermons - Muir, James, The Virtuous Woman. 1 pamphlet (partial). (Box 240-7)
  - Sermons - Ravenscroft, John S., Rev., at St. Paul's Church, Alexandria, May 11, 1820. 1 pamphlet (bound). (Box 240-7)
  - Ships and Shipping - Alexandria Steam Ferry Co., stock, 1839. 1 piece. (Box 240-7)
  - Ships and Shipping - Enrolment certificate of the Maria, 1796. 1 piece. (Box 240-7)
  - Ships and Shipping - Mt. Vernon & Marshall Hall Steamboat Co., timetable. 1 piece. (Box 240-7)
  - Ships and Shipping - Steam Boat Phenix, stocks, 1847. 2 pieces. (Box 240-7)
  - Stationery - Envelope to Miss Katherine Uhler, December 24, 1931. 1 piece. (Box 240-7)
  - Stock Records - Alexandria Stockholders, 1855-1861. 1 book (covers missing). (Box 240-7)
  - Synagogues - Agudas Achim Congregation, T.V. Frolics of 1951. 1 piece. (Box 240-7)
  - Tariffs - Whig Principles, No. 1, 1844. 7 pages from book. (Box 240-7)
  - Theaters - Virginia Theater, inaugural program, 1947. 1 pamphlet. (Box 240-7)
  - Transportation - Alexandria Marine Railway Co., stocks, 1849-1851. 3 pieces. (Box 240-7)
  - Utilities - Alexandria Light & Power, invoices, 1919-1926. 2 pieces. Donated in 1997. (Box 240-7)
  - Utilities - Alexandria Water Company, invoice, 1926. 1 piece. Donated in 1997. (Box 240-7)
  Series 2
- Legal size documents,1752-1993.
  - Account Books - Hodgson, William and James Sanderson, 1801-1805. 1 book. (Box 240A-1)
  - Account Books - Robert Bell's Sons Offset Printers, 1837-1838. 1 book. (Box 240A-1)
  - Account Books - Unknown skilled laborer, ca. 1888-1891. 1 book. Purchased in 1996. (Box 240A-2)
  - Advertising - Alexandria Theatre, 1817. 1 piece. (Box 240A-2)
  - Banks - Bank of Potomac, contract, 1805. 1 piece. (Box 240A-2)
  - Buildings - Southeast corner of Wolfe and Water Streets, deed, 1845. 2 pieces. (Box 240A-2)
  - Businesses - Herbert Bryant Reliable Fertilizers, flier, 1880. 1 piece. (Box 240A-2)
  - Businesses - Business statements (photocopies, most relating to accounts of E.E. Connor), 1850s-1890s. 106 pages. (Box 240A-2)
    H.A. Bowman; E.S. Leadbeater & Sons; Loudoun National Bank; Worth Hulfish & Sons, Inc.; A. Davis, Jr.; Jno. T. Creighton & Son; Thomas Perry; Washington & Co.; J. Grigg & Co.; Kincheloe & Bruin; Adams Express Company; Thomas Lannon; W. Makely; Reinhard & Co.; Chas. King & Son Co. Inc.; M. Bossart; Bank of the Old Dominion; William H. May; Walton, Whann & Co.; E.H. Chase & Co.; Gregory & Co.; E.E. Downham & Co.; S.H. Janney & Son; Roach & Washington; f.G. Swaine; Charles W. Green; Harlow & Bro.; George R. Hill & Co.; E.E. Downham & Co.; B.F. Peake & Co.; John J. Jamieson & Co.; Winchester Boot & Shoe Factory.
  - Businesses - R. Donaldson's Improved Lime Kiln, drawing, 1863. 1 piece. (Box 240A-2)
  - Businesses - Dr. Orlando Fairfax and John Leadbeater, invoice, 1850. 1 piece. (Box 240A-2)
  - Businesses - Johnson & Keefer, Bank of Potomac note, 1847. 1 piece. (Box 240A-2)
  - Businesses - Woodward & Lothrop, Suburban Spectator, 1952. 1 pamphlet. (Box 240A-2)
  - Civil War - Slave pen, consolidated morning report, February 1, 1866. 1 piece. (Box 240A-2)
  - Confederate Monument - R.E. Lee Camp, C.V. Monument, official program, 1889. 1 piece. (Box 240A-2)
  - Correspondence - Appich, Daniel Harrison, 1865. 1 piece (photocopy). (Box 240A-2)
  - Correspondence - Bowyer, John C. from Lewis Cass, 1848. 1 piece. (Box 240A-2)
  - Correspondence - Bowyer, John C. from William Greer, 1858. 4 pieces. (Box 240A-2)
  - Correspondence - Bowyer, John C. from Hugh C. McLaughlin, 1858. 2 pieces. (Box 240A-2)
  - Correspondence - Brent, Daniel Carroll to John Fitzgerald, March 1, 1784. 1 piece. (Box 240A-2)
  - Correspondence - Cazenove letter re: events of August 1814, surrender of Alexandria. 13-page original letter with 42 pages of handwritten transcription and notes. (Box 240A-2)
  - Correspondence - Fairfax, Bryan to his wife, September 23, 1798. 7 pages (photocopy). Donated by Monimia Fairfax MacRae. (Box 240A-2)
  - Correspondence - Hepburn, Moses, 1846. 3 pages (photocopy). (Box 240A-2)
  - Correspondence - Ramsay, J.W., letter fragment, n.d. 2 pieces. (Box 240A-2)
  - Correspondence - Snowden, DeWilton, 1848. 1 piece. (Box 240A-2)
  - Correspondence - Shay, S. King, 1851-1852. 2 pieces. (Box 240A-2)
  - Correspondence - Vowell, John and Thomas Vowell, 1793-1799. 2 pieces. Donated in 1941. (Box 240A-2)
  - Diaries - Eastlack, Andrew W., 1857-1858. 1 item (photocopy). (Box 240A-2)
  - Financial Papers - Grigsby, Alexander S., 1861. 5 pieces with 8 photocopies. (Box 240A-2)
  - Fund Raising - Court House Fund subscription list (transcript), 1752. 1 piece. (Box 240A-2)
  - History 1815-1861 - Alexandria Artillery Company, 1842. 2 pieces and photocopies. (Box 240A-2)
  - Legal Papers - Alexander, Charles, deeds, 1811. 16 pages. (Box 240A-2)
  - Legal Papers - Fairfax County, Virginia, list of deeds and probates, 1770-1771. 3 pieces and photocopies. (Box 240A-2)
  - Legal Papers - Foote, William H., 1837-1851. 9 pieces. (Box 240A-2)
  - Legal Papers - Apprenticeship indenture, James McCormick to John Bogue, June 5, 1797. 1 piece. (Box 240A-2)
  - Legal Papers - Personal property interrogatories (form used to report property subject to taxation), 1883. 1 piece. (Box 240A-2)
  - Legal Papers - Recommendation of Edward Smythe as Fish, Beef & Pork Inspector for Alexandria, March 8, 1844. 1 piece. Gift of Timothy Callahan, 1998. (Box 240A-2)
  - Legal Papers - Ringgold, Tench, Justice of the Peace certificate, 1841. 1 piece. (Box 240A-2)
  - Legal Papers - Thompson, Johan, promissory note, 1802. 1 piece. (Box 240A-2)
  - Magazines - Virginia, First in the Heart of the Nation, Vol. 5 No. 2, Summer 1930. 1 magazine. (Box 240A-3)
  - Miscellanea - Fairfax, Randolph, copybook. 2 books. (Box 240A-3)
  - Music - All Quiet Along the Potomac To-Night, 1863. 1 piece sheet music and photocopy. (Box 240A-3)
  - Music - Col. Ellsworth's Funeral March and Ellsworth: Tribute to teh Memory of the Late Colonel Ellsworth, 1861. 2 pieces sheet music. (Box 240A-3)
  - Music - privately bound collection of sheet music, 19th century. 1 book. (Box 240A-3)
  - Organizations - Andrew Jackson Lodge 120 A.F.&A.M., bulletin, 1990. 1 piece. (Box 240A-3)
  - Organizations - Mount Vernon Guards, minute book, 1842-1855. 1 book. (Box 240A-3)
  - Organizations - Arlington Lodge 756, Alexandria, VA. 1 book. (Box 240A-3)
  - Organizations - Children of the Confederacy, membership charter, 1898. 1 piece (photocopy). (Box 240A-3)
  - Organizations - Friendship Fire Company, minute book and membership, 1925-1936. 73 pages (photocopies). (Box 240A-3)
  - Organizations - Friendship Fire House, guides and programs, 1961-1993. 13 pamphlets and fliers. (Box 240A-3)
  - Organizations - Washington National Monument Society. 2 pieces. (Box 240A-3)
  - Personal Papers - Fitzhugh, William H., correspondence, 1820-1870. 4 pieces (photocopies). (Box 240A-4)
  - Personal Papers - Gardner, Eulalie, 1940-1943. 7 pieces. (Box 240A-4)
  - Personal Papers - Hendricks, Anne Simpson (Mrs. Thomas A.), 1942-1981. 10 pieces. (Box 240A-4)
  - Railroads - Washington Alexandria & Mt. Vernon Electric Railway, advertisement, 1892. 1 piece. (Box 240A-4)
  - Retrocession - President James K. Pllk to Virginia Governor William Smith, drafts of letters, 1846. 7 pieces. (Box 240A-4)
  - Retrocession - Retrocession petition, 1841. 2 pieces. (Box 240A-4)
  - Schools - Alexandria Academy, Tree memorial correspondence, 1928-1932. Approximately 50 pieces. (Box 240A-4)
  - Schools - Alexandria High School, blank report card form, ca. 18??. 1 piece. (Box 240A-4)
  - Schools - Alexandria High School, report card, 1857. 1 piece. (Box 240A-4)
  Series 3
- Oversize documents,1749-1995.
  - Advertising - Richmond, Fredericksburg & Potomac Railroad & Steamboat Line, 1856. 1 piece. (Box 240B-1)
  - Alexandria Theatre - playbills and posters: Battle of Hexham, Magpie & The Maid, Every One Has His Fault. 2 pieces. (Box 240B-1)
  - Architecture - Supplementary Report on the Extension and Completion of the United States Capitol in Relation to the Dome, Carrere and Hastings, 1904. 1 pamphlet. (Box 240B-1)
  - Correspondence - African-Americans - B. Wheat, William Morrill, James Entwisle, 1841. 1 piece. (Box 240B-1)
  - Correspondence - Custis, George Washington Parke, 1823. 2 pieces. (Box 240B-1)
  - Correspondence - Miller, Mary Moore Stabler, 1850. 1 piece. (Box 240B-1)
  - Correspondence - Henley, David, 1817. 1 piece. (Box 240B-1)
  - Correspondence - Stone Margaret, 1839. 1 piece. Purchased in 1991. (Box 240B-1)
  - Correspondence - Ward Committees of Alexandria to mayor of Washington, DC, October 20, 1814. 1 piece. Purchased in 2004. (Box 240B-1)
  - Diplomas - Arthur James Mourot, West Virginia University Bachelor of Science, 1929. 1 piece. (Box 240B-1)
  - Directories - Alexandria Sesqui-Centennial Business Directory, 1899. 1 pamphlet. (Box 240B-1)
  - Lee Family - Coat of arms. 1 piece. (Box 240B-1)
  - Legal Papers - Apprenticeship indenture, surgery/apothecary, 1764. 1 piece. (Box 240B-1)
  - Legal Papers - Buckland, William, deed for negro man Oxford and 129-acre parcel of land known as Drowns(?), 1767. 1 piece. (Box 240B-1)
  - Legal Papers - Apprenticeship indenture, house carpenter/joiner, September 13, 1800. 1 piece. (Box 240B-1)
  - Legal Papers - Carson, James, Militia of the District of Columbia commission, 1814. 1 piece. (Box 240B-1)
  - Legal Papers - Coryell, George, deed for property on west side of Water Street and south side of Duke Street (lot 4 in James Mercer plat), 1767. 1 piece. (Box 240B-1)
  - Legal Papers - Green, Edward, certificate of citizenship, 1830. 1 piece. (Box 240B-1)
  - Legal Papers - Green, Edward, Collector of Customs commission, 1846. 1 piece. (Box 240B-1)
  - Legal Papers - Fairfax, Thomas, deed to Valentine Power, 1773. 1 piece. (Box 240B-1)
  - Legal Papers - Lunt, Samuel, list of claims against his estate, 1853. 1 piece. (Box 240B-1)
  - Legal Papers - Petition to incorporate Alexandria, 1778. 10 copy pages on photo paper and transcript. (Box 240B-1)
  - Legal Papers - Act to establish Alexandria, 1749. 3 copy pages. (Box 240B-1)
  - Legal Papers - Violett, Thomas, estate inventory, March 9, 1805. 1 piece. (Box 240B-1)
  - Music - Ellen Terry Waltz, compliments of Alexandria Dime Museum, 1883. 1 piece of sheet music. (Box 240B-1)
  - Organizations - Alexandria Water Company, membership roster, 1854-1895. 1 book. (Box 240B-1)
  - Organizations - Alexandria Fire Department, Statistics of Fires, 1950-1957. 1 book. (Box 240B-1)
  - Organizations - Alexandria Fire Department, Statistics of Fires, 1935-1937. 1 book. (Box 240B-1)
  - Organizations - Alexandria Washington Lodge No. 22, certificate of membership for Alexander Murray, 1866. 1 piece. (Box 240B-1)
  - Organizations - Star Fire Company, Articles, 1821. 1 piece. (Box 240B-1)
  - Posters - Exhibit of antiques and family heirlooms, Hugh McGuire. 1 piece. (Box 240B-1)
  - Railroads - Alexandria, Loudoun, and Hampshire Railroad Co., handbill opposing Manassas Gap Railroad Co. 1 piece. (Box 240B-2)
  - Schools - Belle Haven Institute, Mattie Hannon diplomas, 1877-1878. 2 pieces. (Box 240B-2)
  - Schools - George Washington High School, student lists, 1903-1912. 2 books. (Box 240B-2)
  - Schools - T.C. Williams High School, awards and honors poster, 1995. 1 piece. (Box 240B-2)
  - Sesquicentennial - Business directory and official program, 1899. 1 pamphlet. (Box 240B-2)
  - Speeches - Harrison, William Henry, inaugural speech, 1841. 1 piece of fabric. (Box 240B-2)
  - United States National Guard - First Virginia Infantry, Company G membership roster, 1916. 1 piece. (Box 240B-2)
  - Washington Theater - Way To Get Married poster, 1821. 1 piece. (Box 240B-2)
  - Wills - Ford, Josiah B., May 10, 1824. 1 piece. (Box 240B-2)